So I want to move on and introduce
our next presenter.
We have Andrew Burrell
from the University of Technology Sydney.
Welcome, Andrew.
I'll turn it over to you.
Thanks very much.
I'll just get my
sharing.
There you go.
Yeah.
So Andrew Borrow from the University
of Technology Sydney School of Design,
streaming in from the unceded country
of the Grigol and people.
There's some nice flow on
from the ripples project,
I think, in where I'm going to go today.
So twice again for renters is a discrete
outcome
of an ongoing series of experiments
with digital and material outcomes
investigating distributed authorship via
generative world
building.
One of the tensions this work holds
is the site of authorship
within a dense ecology of text.
Text is archive
Texas extraction, generative text,
computational frameworks
and technological infrastructures.
Sitting alongside this tension,
and ultimately more interesting
to me, is where creativity sits
within this distributed field.
With the work, elements of agency
are handed off to the machine,
and the notion of what constitutes
the machine is also in question.
It is.
It is in part the large language models
I'll introduce shortly,
but it's also a much wider ecology
of machine code and infrastructure.
And the possibilities they afford
parentheses, as
as are other projects in this series,
is based around a 50,000 word novella,
which is regarded
as canon across the project.
It was written without revision and
has not been edited past his first draft.
It was also written in what I consider
a form of automatic writing,
bounded by a simple rule
set of preexisting chapter based
timeline with an exponential
chronological progression.
The text, as canon, becomes
the curated source material
of the overall project,
and has been analyzed
and annotated in many different ways.
At the heart of the rents
is an interface
to local large language models.
It can, and text becomes both the material
from which prompts are built and a foil
to to these generated texts
to prepare the canon for integration
into the workflow towards the large
language models, it was fragmented,
processed and augmented via
a series of distant
reading and text manipulation devices.
The curated automatic text becomes
curated into more structured content,
often as a list and grouping of text.
These processes
include a set of distant reading
methods
that are detailed on the current slide.
These lists enter the
project as a sort of meta canon
that can be drawn on in
many different ways
within the world building framework.
They become integrated into the formation
for prompts
for two agents
driven by local large language models.
These are generic out of the box models,
and this is important
for both the knowledge they contain
and their slow differentiation
as the As agents via the individual
individual narratives as memories.
Of these two agents,
one takes on the role of the planet
varieties, the other
the role of a cartographer.
Within the logic of this world.
Building varieties acts as a game master
and the cartographer
at the role of a player.
It is the model's knowledge of these roles
within traditional text based
adventure games that makes a world
building possible, and coherent.
System
prompts establish a text adventure logic,
with these canonical fragments
injected into the prompts as a narrative,
the world builds over a series of 50
turns.
Accumulative memory builds
as each response is added to the system,
prompts.
The process, defines and redefines
the bounds of the ongoing exchange
taking place.
John Potts
described
some of my earlier work of generative text
as placing myself in the role of damage,
where texts would be created
by setting initial conditions
and stepping back to watch what emerges.
Extending on this and extending
this damage roll into the rents.
The Demiurge helps us imagine
where or the ship might be cited.
While it's tempting to do so, we do not.
We do not need to move this authorship
to the large language model
it sits before we even reach the model
in the world
building flow,
though it does extend into it.
The relocation of authorship begins
in the canon, moves through
natural language processing
and into the creation of prompt,
and finally can be found to
in the infrastructure.
The site of the authorship
is further distributed across decisions
around the use of extracted fragments,
the prescribed rules the system prompt
evokes, and what we initially admitted
into the canon.
Authorship is also distributed
to the many hundreds of authors
of interactive fiction,
following the rules that emerge
collectively across the of text adventure
games.
It also sits before them
with the authors of infrastructure,
both hardware and software
that afforded these rules
without the command line interface,
for example, and what it forwarded,
variants would not exist.
The big unknown question
then is what happens to
the Demiurge is intention
based on the known canon
as archive,
when it collides with the unknowable
archive of the
large language model weights.
I subtitle this talk with a term
arising out of the conference's
theme of bounded unsupervised
variants is bounded by the framework
supervised
in its prompting
and unsupervised in its ongoing unfolding.
The constant feedback loop
of adding to prompts with its own
outcome adds
layers of depth to the resultant text
and a coherent memory
across the emerging narrative.
Another side of this work,
and of a more central,
ongoing concern in my practice,
is that I describe this ongoing,
more than human collaboration as an active
and ongoing act of creativity.
I'm not proposing the large language model
as a creative subject in its own right,
but with within a wider networked context,
it plays
an important role in the creative outcome
that would not be possible without it.
What I
am pointing to is
that the weights of these models function
as an archive
that no one fully knows or controls.
I see the more than human as being able
to encompass
that disruptive providence
in this.
It does not need to be an equivalent
of what we might consider to be
human creativity.
It is.
It is its own form of creativity.
This this rests
on a relational view of creativity.
One way the network of cannon extraction,
prompt and model
become a generative site in its own right.
Creativity does not sit solely in
any one individual, and it never has.
I know this is a contested position,
but the disagreement
it provokes is one of the possibilities
that this work is exploring.
I want to close with a reflection
on a single moment from over into session.
The cartographer asks a routine question
about a detail
introduced by one of the agents
earlier in the narrative.
Barrientos answers answer includes
a limp
torso is now in Eric Lupine's possession.
But where did it go?
Rainbow is a protagonist
within the canon and appears
frequently in the generated text.
Eric Lupine existing
canon only as a secondary
character named but undeveloped.
What happens
next has not been invented from nothing.
It's an emergence from a space
the canon left open.
Across the loving exchange,
lupine acquires
an office and encrypted data pad,
a role in a wider plot involving something
the model pulls from canon,
namely a sect leader
and a completely non-canon Nexus protocol.
Ultimately,
none of this was altered by me.
But importantly, all of it is consistent
with the elements I did.
Author.
The model found room
inside the archive of its training data,
and the agent's ongoing memory
to create these aspects of a novel world.
Nobody decided Eric
the Pine would have an office,
a datapad, a place in a hidden plot.
Authorship set the conditions under
which that would, that could that world
could grow, and the wider network
ecology fostered this emergence over time.
Authorship.
Invariant is relocated
through the many layers of its making.
This relocation happens
in the writing of canon. The
the curation via distant reading,
the historical and current infrastructure
and flows into the rules
that have been set, and the archive
that sits across all of these spaces
twice again. Variants.
Does this redistribution of all
and agency across a wide area of human
and more than human collaborators,
for which I call myself part?
Thanks very much.